{
  "title": "Theory_of_Computation - Undecidability",
  "duration": 47,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Undecidability",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following sets:<br><br>\nS1: Set of all recursively enumerable languages over the alphabet {0, 1}.<br>\nS2: Set of all syntactically valid C programs.<br>\nS3: Set of all languages over the alphabet {0, 1}.<br>\nS4: Set of all non-regular languages over the alphabet {0, 1}.\n<br><br>\nWhich of the above sets are uncountable? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>S1 and S2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>S3 and S4</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>S2 and S3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>S1 and S4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>S3 and S4</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302814/gate2019-cs-34#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Let L(R) be the language represented by regular expression R. Let L(G) be the language\ngenerated by a context free grammar G. Let L (M) be the language accepted by a Turning\nmachine M. Which of the following decision problems are undecidable ?<br><br>\nI. Given a regular expression R and a string w, is w\\(\\in \\)L(R)?<br>\nII. Given a context-free grammar G, L(G)=\\(\\phi\\)?<br>\nIII. Given a context-free grammar G, is L(G)=\\(\\Sigma\\)*  for some alphabet \\(\\Sigma\\)?<br>\nIV. Given a Turning machine M and a string w, is w\\(\\in\\)L(M)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I and IV only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II and III only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>II, III and IV only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>III and IV only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>III and IV only</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118605/gate2017-2-41#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Which  of the following decision problems are undecidable?<br>\nI. Given NFAs N1 and N2, is L(N1)\\(\\cap\\)L(N2) = \\(\\phi\\)?<br>\nII. Given a CFG G = (N,\\(\\Sigma \\),P,S)  and a string  \\(x \\in\\Sigma ^*\\), does  \\(x \\in\\) L(G)?<br>\nIII. Given CFGs G1 and G2, is L(G1) = L(G2)?<br>\nIV. Given a TM M, is L(M) = \\(\\phi\\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I and IV only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II and III only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>III and IV only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>II and IV only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>III and IV only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39651/gate2016-1-17#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following problems is undecidable? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Deciding if a given context-free grammar is ambiguous</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Deciding if a given string is generated by a given context-free grammar</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Deciding if the language generated by a given context-free grammar is empty</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Deciding if the language generated by a given context-free grammar is finite.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Deciding if a given context-free grammar is ambiguous</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2069/gate2014-3-35#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(\\Sigma\\) be a finite non-empty alphabet and let \\(2^{\\Sigma^{*}}\\) be the power set of \\(\\Sigma^{*}\\) . Which one of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both \\(2^{\\Sigma^{*}}\\) and \\(\\Sigma^{*}\\) are countable</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(2^{\\Sigma^{*}}\\) is countable \\(\\Sigma^{*}\\) is uncountable</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2^{\\Sigma^{*}}\\)  is uncountable and \\(\\Sigma^{*}\\) is countable</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Both \\(2^{\\Sigma^{*}}\\)  and \\(\\Sigma^{*}\\) are uncountable</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2^{\\Sigma^{*}}\\)  is uncountable and \\(\\Sigma^{*}\\) is countable</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2050/gate2014-3-16#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(A \\leq _{m}B\\) denotes that language A is mapping reducible (also known as many-to-one reducible) to language B. Which one of the following is FALSE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>If \\(A\\leq _{m}B\\) and B is recursive then A is recursive</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>If \\(A\\leq _{m}B\\) and A is undecidable then B is undecidable</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>If \\(A\\leq _{m}B\\) and B is recursively enumerable then A is recursively enumerable.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>If \\(A\\leq _{m}B\\) and B is not recursively enumerable then A is not recursively enumerable</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>If \\(A\\leq _{m}B\\) and B is not recursively enumerable then A is not recursively enumerable</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1972/gate2014-2-16#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following is/are undecidable? <br>\n1. G is a CFG. Is L(G) = \\(\\Phi\\)? <br>\n2. G is a CFG. Is L(G) = \\(\\Sigma ^{*}\\) ? <br>\n3. M is a Turing machine. Is L(M) regular? <br>\n4. A is a DFA and N is an NFA. Is L(A) = L(N)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3 only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>3 and 4 only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1, 2 and 3 only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2 and 3 only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>2 and 3 only</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1553/gate2013-41#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following problems are decidable?<br>\n1) Does a given program ever produce an output? <br>\n2) If L is a context-free language, then, is \\(\\bar{L}\\) also context-free?<br>\n3) If L is a regular language, then, is \\(\\bar{L}\\) also regular? <br>\n4) If L is a recursive language, then, is \\(\\bar{L}\\) also recursive? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2012)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1, 2, 3, 4</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1,2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2,3,4</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>3,4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>3,4</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1608/gate2012-24#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following are decidable? <br><br>\nI. Whether the intersection of two regular languages is infinite <br>\nII. Whether a given context-free language is regular <br>\nIII. Whether two push-down automata accept the same language <br>\nIV. Whether a given grammar is context-free <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I and II</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I and IV</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>II and III</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>II and IV</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>I and IV</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/408/gate2008-10#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following problems is undecidable? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Membership problem for CFGs.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Ambiguity problem for CFGs.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Finiteness problem for FSAs.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Equivalence problem for FSAs.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Ambiguity problem for CFGs.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1204/gate2007-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Consider three decision problems P1, P2 and P3. It is known that P1 is decidable and P2 is undecidable. Which one of the following is true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>P3 is decidable if P1 is reducible to P3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>P3 is undecidable if P3 is reducible to P2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>P3 is undecidable if P2 is reducible to P3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>P3 is decidable if P3 is reducible to P2's complement</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>P3 is undecidable if P2 is reducible to P3</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1375/gate2005-45#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Consider two languages L1 and L2 each on the alphabet \\(\\Sigma\\). Let \\(f:\\Sigma \\rightarrow \\Sigma\\) be a polynomial time computable bijection such that \\((\\forall x)[x \\in L1 \\; \\; if \\; \\; f(x) \\in L2]\\). Further, let \\(f^{-1}\\) be also polynomial time computable. Which of the following CANNOT be true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2003)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L1 \\(\\in\\) P and L2 is finite</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L1 \\(\\in\\)\nNP and L2 \\(\\in\\) P</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>L1 is undecidable and L2 is decidable</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>L1 is recursively enumerable and L2 is recursive</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>L1 is undecidable and L2 is decidable</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/356/gate2003-52#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following is not decidable? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Given a Turing machine M, a string s and an integer k, M accepts s within k steps</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Equivalence of two given Turing machines</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Language accepted by a given finite state machine is not empty</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Language generated by a context free grammar is non-empty</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Equivalence of two given Turing machines</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2261/gate1997-6-5\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following statements is false? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The Halting Problem of Turing machines is undecidable</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Determining whether a context-free grammar is ambiguous is undecidable</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Given two arbitrary context-free grammars \\(G_1\\) and \\(G_2\\)it is undecidable whether \\(L(G_1) = L(G_2)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Given two regular grammars \\(G_1\\) and \\(G_2\\) it is undecidable whether \\(L(G_1) = L(G_2)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Given two regular grammars \\(G_1\\) and \\(G_2\\) it is undecidable whether \\(L(G_1) = L(G_2)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2713/gate1996-1-9\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct alternatives (More than one may be correct).<br>It is undecidable whether: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1990)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>An arbitrary Turing machine halts after 100 steps.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>A Turing machine prints a specific letter.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>A Turing machine computes the products of two numbers</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>A Turing machine prints a specific letter.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/84835/gate1990-3-vii\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 16,
          "question": "<p>Answer the following questions:<br>Which of the following problems are undecidable? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1989)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Membership problem in context-free languages.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Whether a given context-free language is regular.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Whether a finite state automation halts on all inputs.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Membership problem for type 0 languages.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Whether a given context-free language is regular.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/87123/gate1989-3-iii\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 17,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following problems are un-decidable?<br>[MSQ] <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1989)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Membership problem in context-free languages.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Whether a given context-free language is regular.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Whether a finite state automation halts on all inputs.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Membership problem for type 0 languages.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Whether a given context-free language is regular.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/87123/gate1989-3-iii\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}